Guide to the M. Esther Harding Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
M. Esther Harding collection
1920-1970
GEN MSS 939
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.92
(18 boxes)
Harding, M. Esther (Mary Esther), 1888-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the C. G. Jung Institute of New York on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
M. Esther Harding
M. Esther Harding (1888-1971) was an American psychoanalyst. She was early adherent to the theories of C. G. Jung and the first significant practitioner of Jungian psychoanalysis in the United States.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series: I. Jungian Seminar Records, 1923-1937. II. Analytical Notes and Journals, 1920-1970. III. Writings, 1922-1970. IV. Correspondence and Criticism, 1946-1969. V. Writings of Others, 1971. VI. Photographs, 1909-1968. VII. Artwork. VIII. Printed Material.
Jungian psychology; Psychoanalysis; Harding, M. Esther (Mary Esther), 1888-1971; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961
- Jungian seminar records, 1923-1937; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by date of the seminar documented.
  - "Dreams of Peter Blobbs" Seminar, September 1920, Sennen Cove, Land's End, Cornwall, England
    - M. Esther Harding seminar dinner speech, 1937 October (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Describes the 1920 seminar.
  - Human Relationships Seminar, July 14-26, 1923, Polzeath, England (The Cornwall Seminar)
    - Manuscript and typescript notes by M. Esther Harding, Kristine Mann, and Cary de Angelo, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Fabric and board wrapper for Cornwall Seminar notes (Box 18 (Oversize))
  - Analytic Psychology Seminar, March 23-June 6, 1925, Zürich, Switzerland
    - Manuscript notes by Harding, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Dreams and Symbolism Seminar, July 25-August 7, 1925, Swanage, England (The Swanage Seminar)
    - Kristine Mann seminar journal/transcript, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Manuscript and typescript notes by Harding and possibly Eleanor Bertine, 1925 (Box 1)
  - "Diaries in C.G.'s Seminars, 1926-7", 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    Manuscript notes of conversations with Jung, possibly by Eleanor Bertine, not specific to any seminars.
  - Dreams Analysis Seminars, 1928-1930, Zürich, Switzerland
    - Seminar I, November 7-December 12, 1928
      - Typescrpt notes by Harding, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Seminar II, October 8-November 27, 1929
      - Manuscript and typescript notes by Harding, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Psychological Analysis of Nietzsche's Zarathustra Seminar, June 3, 1936, Zürich, Switzerland
    - "Answer to a Question concerning the Archaic Elements in the Self", 1936 (Box 1)
      Typescript by Harding with annotations.
  - Unidentified seminar
    - Manuscript notes, possibly by Eleanor Bertine, undated (Box 1)
- Analytical notes and journals, 1920-1970; Series II
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Analytical notes and journals, 1920-1923 (Box 2)
  - Analytical notes and journals, 1924-1933 (Box 3)
  - Analytical notes and journals, 1933-1970 (Box 4)
- Writings, 1922-1970; Series III
  - "Some Aspects of Personality from the Point of View of the Psychoanalyst," given before the Cosmopolitan Club, London, 1922 (Box 5)
  - "Paper for the London Psychological Club", 1922 October 5 (Box 5)
  - "She:" A Portrait of the Anima. A Critical Analysis of the Novel by Sir Henry Rider Haggard, first read in the Seminar by C.G. Jung, Kusnacht-Zurich, 1925 (Box 5)
  - "Psychoanalyzing The Captive", in the new Ever magazine, 1926 December (Box 5)
    Typescripts and clippings
  - "A Short Survey of Dr. Jung's Article – Redemption Ideas in Alchemy", 1927 (Box 5)
  - Typscript of a book review, " Two Essays on Analytical Psychology by C.G. Jung," which appeard in The Nation, December 12, 1928 (Box 5)
  - Typescript of a book review, " Contributions to Analytical Psychology by C.G. Jung," which appeared in The New York Times Book Review, May 12, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Typescript of a book review, "'The Ordinary Man and the Unconscious' review of Two Essays on Analytical Psychology by C.G. Jung / translated by H.G. and C.F. Baynes," possibly published in The Dial, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Clipping of a book review, " Jung's Two Essays on Analytic Psychology and Contributions to Analytic Psychology ," which appeared in The New Republic on February 6, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Clipping of a book review, " Gestalt Psychology's Challenge to the Behaviorists by Wolfgang Kohler," which appeared in The New York Times Book Review, May 19, 1929 (Box 5)
  - "Christmas Message from the Point of View of Analytical Psychology," in Concern, Vol. 12, no. 10, December 1970, p. 15-20, published by United Presbyterian Women. (Box 5)
  - Address list, undated (Box 5)
- Correspondence and criticism, 1946-1969; Series IV (Box 5)
  Texts that include criticism of Harding's writings and correspondence relating to publishing, including letters from Random House, Bollingen Foundation, Indian Psycho-Therapeutical Society, and Paul Mellon.
- Writings of others, 1971; Series V
  - Memorials for M. Esther Harding, 1971 (Box 6)
    Includes program for a memorial meeting, October 22, 1971, at the United Engineering Center, New York, given by the Psychology Club of New York City, NYAAP, and C.G. Jung Foundation for Analytical Psychology, and remarks by William Kennedy at Harding's funeral, May 15, 1971.
- Photographs, 1909-1968; Series VI
  - Photograph albums
    - "C. G. Jung Vol. 1" (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - "C. G. Jung, volume 3" (Box 8 (Oversize))
    - "Bailey Island," Vol. 12, 1968 (Box 9 (Oversize))
    - "M. Esther Harding, Bailey Island, Maine, August 5, 1968" (Box 10 (Oversize))
      Inscribed "To Esther Harding on the occasion of her 80th birthday with love and esteem from her friends and colleagues."
    - "Dr. Harding, Dr. Bertine, Dr. Mann," Vol. 13 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Album of portraits of C. G. Jung (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Loose photographs
    - Photographs of Esther Harding, C.G. Jung, etc., 1909, 1955-1957, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - Photographs of Esther Harding, C.G. Jung, etc., 1936-1958, undated (Box 14)
    - Photographs of C.G. Jung, etc., 1956-1957, undated (Box 15)
- Artwork, undated; Series VII
  - Oil painting of C. G. Jung, undated (Box 16 (Oversize))
- Printed materials, undated; Series VIII
  - The Life and Work of St. Paul by Frederic W. Farrar, undated (Box 17)
    Shrewsbury High School prize "Old Girls" presented by Archdeacon Maude to Mary Esther Harding.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 17)